today we welcome to the program John
kiriaku former CIA counter-terrorism
officer turned whistleblower who has
some very interesting things to say
about pardons that may or may not have
been offered by a former lawyer to a
former president but but we will get to
that John really great having you on I
appreciate your time oh thanks so much
for the invitation happy to do it so to
give the audience some context to start
with you were a CIA officer in 2007 six
years after 9 11. uh you blew the
whistle on what was effectively torture
that was being used by the CIA you were
I believe the first federal government
employee to do so you were not
ultimately prosecuted for disclosing
that but I'll give you the opportunity
to weigh in maybe for political reasons
you were not prosecuted for that but
ultimately uh I believe you say as
retaliation you were prosecuted talk to
us about what you knew your involvement
why you decided to blow the whistle to
start with
it's actually quite a long story that
I'm going to make very very short uh I
was uh I was a senior Cia
counter-terrorism officer after 9 11 I
was the the chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
I led a series of raids there that
resulted in the capture of Abu zubaida
who we believed at the time was the
number three abusive beta was also the
first person
um
captured by the CIA who had been ranked
internally as a high value Target and
because he was the first he was also the
first to undergo uh torture with the CIA
at the time was calling enhanced
interrogation techniques uh I objected
to that I thought it was torture I
thought it was illegal I still think
it's illegal besides being immoral and
uh and unethical
and um
and my objections were uh overridden and
ignored I left the CIA in 2004 I
formally resigned in 2005. and waited
for somebody to come out and say
something about this program it was just
so patently illegal to me I thought
certainly somebody will come out and say
something nobody did
and so then in December of 2007 in
response to a request from from Brian
Ross at ABC News I said something I went
on a nationally televised uh uh show and
I said that the CIA was torturing its
prisoners I said that torture was
official U.S government policy and I
said that the policy had been personally
approved by the president himself as you
might imagine the CIA reported me to the
FBI for leaking classified information
and the FBI investigated me from the
very next day December of 2007 until
December of 2008. uh after that
year-long investigation the FBI sent my
attorneys what's called a declination
letter declining to prosecute me they
said that the information was not
classified that it was already out there
it had been published by Human Rights
Watch Amnesty International and the
international Committee of the Red Cross
and they dropped the case
I did not know that three weeks later
when Barack Obama became president and
John Brennan an old Nemesis of mine
became the deputy National Security
adviser that Brennan asked the justice
department to secretly reopen the case
against me and so they investigated me
for another three years and then in uh
January of 2012 I was arrested and
charged with five felonies coming out of
that ABC news interview
three counts of Espionage one count of
violating the intelligence identities
protection act of 1982 and one count of
making a false statement we were never
really clear as to what the false
statement was supposed to have been that
charge was dropped I absolutely did not
commit Espionage and those charges were
dropped but uh they got me on a
technicality uh I had confirmed the
surname of a former colleague of mine to
a journalist who wanted to interview him
for a book
and that was the the crime that they got
me on that name was never made public
and other senior Cia officers who had
done the same thing
like David Petraeus for example who
revealed the names of of 10 covert
operatives to his adulterous girlfriend
uh was never prosecuted but you know I
always maintained that I was prosecuted
for political reasons and I'm a big boy
I know how Washington works and that was
that was a calculation that John Brennan
and the justice department made to
silence someone who had oppose the
torture program they didn't silence me
they actually empowered me and uh here
we are now all these years later
so so many different things to ask about
with regard to the techniques that were
being used that you blew the whistle on
you talked about there were apparently
discussions about the legality and
ethics and whether these techniques the
use of the techniques is policy was
there ever a discussion about their
effectiveness and whether listen if we
do this stuff they or in most cases he
are just going to tell us what what he
thinks he needs to say in order to get
us to stop was that ever discussed right
that's a great question
um and the answer is uh no not not
in any meaningful depth huh you know in
the in the immediate aftermath of of 9
11. I I think this is something that
most people don't have a full
appreciation for there was at least as
much a desire for Revenge as there was
for information to uh to disrupt future
attacks uh so you know those those very
senior officers those CIA leaders who
had conceived of the torture program had
implemented the torture program and then
briefed it to the oversight committees
on Capitol Hill
um
they didn't care if the prisoner was
going to tell us what he thought we
wanted to hear they figured we would
collect everything that the prisoner
said and then turn it over to the
analysts and let the analysts sort
through it so is there going to be
actionable intelligence in there sure
there is is there going to be garbage
there's going to be a lot more garbage
than there is actionable intelligence
but you're able then to seek that desire
for revenge and collect intelligence at
the same time so it wasn't it wasn't
that it wasn't discussed
because people didn't necessarily
believe we might get nonsense from doing
this it was just that it didn't matter
and we'll kind of sort through it in the
aftermath yeah that's
when it comes to the locations where
some of these things were taking place
colloquially sometimes known as these
black sites yes to the extent you can
talk about it the CIA employees that are
involved in servicing these sites either
directly participating in the in the
torture or not right because these are
locations that presumably need ancillary
Services of different kinds are they
typically in these countries their
entire presence in the countries is it
illegal is it under diplomatic cover or
do they have some nominal other job
while there
that's that's a tough one to answer
without getting in trouble uh there the
the CIA uses a multitude of covers both
official and unofficial this would have
been official cover uh in most cases it
was done with the acquiescence of the
host government ah
um and it wasn't Deep Cover it wasn't
backstopped in any way so if if somebody
if you're sitting next to somebody on a
plane they say what do you do for a
living you say I work for the Department
of Commerce I work for the state
department oh what do you do at the
state department I'm involved in uh in
international trade you know that's so
boring that nine times out of ten
nobody's gonna ask you a follow-up
question right but now if they call the
State Department and ask can you know
can I talk to John kiriaku there there
is no John kiriaku there that's going to
answer the phone so that it's not
backstopped in that way a lot of people
at headquarters covering for you
um now with that said
um I I've said this publicly in the past
and and we know it's true thanks to the
Senate torture report uh there were many
cases in many of these various countries
where black sites existed where the
president or the prime minister of those
countries had no idea that these torture
chambers were were there right in their
territory these were handshake deals
between George Tenet the head of the CIA
and the head of whatever that host
intelligence service was that's how
secret this was and you you said
something also that that I think Bears
repeating because it's true uh very few
very very few CIA officers were actually
physically involved in the torture
program right but there were large
support staffs you know everybody from
secretaries to analysts to doctors and
nurses
um to Communications professionals
they were all there to support the
actual torturers
is there sometimes in fictionalized
accounts of these situations there's
attention portrayed between the
torturers and the doctors where the
doctors say you're you're going too far
and the torture say you know the the
bomb is ticking we've got it and and
it's portrayed in this kind of dramatic
way is is that in any way an accurate
representation of how these things go
Yes actually uh you know I remember in
in the very very earliest days after the
CIA started torturing Elizabeth like the
first week or the first two weeks there
were there were cables coming back being
written by the doctors saying hey wait a
minute I didn't sign up for this this is
a violation of the Hippocratic oath I
want to come home that's called the
curtailment cable where you want to
curtail your current assignment and come
home that's usually a career-ending
decision you're never going to get
promoted again if you curtail but you've
got this ethical dilemma you put your
hand in the air and you swore to First
Do no harm
and now your job is to allow these guys
to torture prisoner to within an inch of
his life and then if they go too far and
his heart stops your job is to bring him
back to life so he can be tortured more
one of the great disappointments for me
in those early days was that even though
doctors objected
most of them didn't do anything about it
they didn't come home uh they didn't
file lawsuits they didn't go to the
Inspector General and file a complaint
they just maintain their silence
did this stuff literally make it
difficult to sleep at night
yes
and not just for me but for a lot of
people you know I remember people coming
back from the secret sites and crying uh
they they suffered from PTSD they had to
take time off work people went on
anti-anxiety medication this was just an
all-around bad idea now with that said
the CIA is full of sociopaths and
Psychopaths who slept just fine at night
so let's talk about the uh pardon you
served your sentence
um you were not going to be entitled to
your CIA retirement benefits as a result
of the prosecution in the sentence and
you
um tell the story of a meeting with Rudy
Giuliani with the possibility of paying
two million dollars for Trump to Pardon
you is that are those the Top Line
details as as we understand them yes
indeed how did this for now just to put
up front even Financial if you were
willing to do it the 2 million didn't
make sense because it seems like the
retirement benefits were worth about
700k is that right okay that's right so
the math didn't make sense how did this
first come to your attention that this
was maybe something that could happen
I uh I had worked hard to try to get
myself in front of Donald Trump to ask
him directly to pardon me my pitch was
Barack Obama ruined my life and you're
the only person that can give it back to
me uh an appeal to his ego exactly yeah
okay so
I I had a supporter in uh in Kentucky
Carlson and Tucker invited me on the
show a dozen times over the course of
the Trump presidency and a dozen times I
went on and listen you know I'm a third
generation Democrat I'm decidedly left
of center but I hate Barack Obama and
that is what uh that's what Tucker
Carlson wanted to hear and I was
perfectly happy to say it so uh Trump
saw me on on Tucker's show one one night
and told uh Jared Kushner to get in
touch with me so
uh his lawyer called my lawyer and we
met uh briefly at his lawyer's office
and uh to make a long story short he was
not helpful not helpful at all and not
even nice about it
so I mentioned to a friend of mine
I need to get to Trump and this Kushner
thing didn't work what should I do and
he said you need to get to Rudy Giuliani
I said actually I know a guy who knows a
guy who can get me in front of Rudy so I
called my friend I said hey can you put
me in front of Rudy Giuliani he said
sure I'll make a call
so I talked to giuliani's uh assistant
or Deputy or a major Domo or whatever it
was that he was calling himself and he
said actually we're going to be in
Washington next week why don't we meet
at the Trump Hotel I said great
naturally yeah that's the only place you
would ever meet with people
so I went to the Trump Hotel and uh you
know the funny thing is that I normally
work from uh I have a live radio show
from 12 to 2 so I said well how about
any time after two o'clock he said no uh
Rudy uh likes to uh you know enjoy the
day and usually by two o'clock he's not
able to do business I just have to do
this it's like in a court for people
only listening John did the drinky
drinky hand gesture when he said that we
just need for what it is that's what he
did
so I said okay that's fine we met at 11
o'clock
and uh we're all sitting there just
making small talk just meaningless Chit
Chat yeah and finally I said so Mr Mayor
there's this issue of of a pardon I
wanted to raise with you and he said
anybody know where the pisser is and he
got up and just walked away
and I said to his assistant what the
heck just happened he wants you to go in
there right
I I was happy to follow him there if
that's what he wanted but his his
assistant said
um you don't talk to Rudy uh directly
about a party don't talk to me and I
talked to Rudy I said okay whatever and
he says Rudy's going to want 2 million
for the pardon and I laughed and I said
listen
I don't have two million dollars I'll
never have two million dollars but even
if I did I wouldn't spend two million
dollars to recover a 700 000 pension
right so we just sat there for a minute
and looked at each other and I said this
this just isn't going to work thank you
for your time Giuliani was walking back
and I said Mr Mayor thank you for your
time I walked out
um
I happened to go to a book uh event that
night a buddy of mine had just come out
with a book and there was this big uh
launch party and I ran into another
friend another whistleblower he said to
me very innocently how was your day
today and I said oh listen to this and I
told him the story that I just told you
he was so enraged
that on his own position
told them that Giuliani had solicited
two million dollars to sell me a pardon
I didn't know that but the FBI never
called me and my friend was then so
outraged that the FBI never called that
he called The New York Times that leaked
it to the New York Times so the New York
Times did call and I decided you know
what this was an illegal act it was a
felony that Giuliani had committed and
so I'm gonna I'm gonna tell the New York
Times what happened and I did as it
turned out Giuliani had done this with
several people but again the FBI wasn't
interested I've never spoken to the FBI
they've never called me they've never
questioned me
um it wasn't until Giuliani was the
subject of a of a civil suit recently
yeah that this came up where the the
plaintiff is alleging that in the course
of pillow talk I suppose
um he told her that he was soliciting
two million dollars for pardons and he
was splitting the money with Donald
Trump I have no idea if that's true let
me ask you a super practical like
logistical question if you had wanted to
go forward with this do you have an
assumption about how the money would be
transferred is it like you bring
physical cash that you get from
somewhere how would they even do it
you know I can't imagine that any
legitimate bank would even let you have
to even if I had two million dollars in
my checking account yeah they they Banks
normally don't even keep more than ten
thousand dollars on hand at any given
time uh you have to actually order it
from the Federal Reserve right and they
and they truck it over it plus there are
money laundering laws where you have to
report to the IRS
any transaction over ten thousand
dollars right so my guess is that it
would have to be electronic in which
case it would have raised red flags in
which case it would have probably
initiated uh an investigation and they
just couldn't have gotten away with
something like that yeah that I mean of
course it raises the question how many
other people were offered this deal how
many took it and I guess we don't know
but you would think that there would be
some trail if that's right if this was
being done regularly in some way
obviously we don't know the answer you
know I'll
apologize because I know
I knew my attorney and I went to see an
FBI agent over over a case of fraud that
I just sort of stumbled over and I I
felt it was my duty to report this this
fraud so I took a thumb drive with me
with thousands of pages of supporting
documents and we went to the Washington
field office to speak to the FBI I'm
five minutes into my explanation of what
we're doing there and this FBI agent
puts up his hands and he says buddy
if this doesn't have the word terrorism
associated with it we're not interested
and I think that's what happened with
Giuliani interesting yeah and that Rings
true to
all of my friends who are in some way
involved in federal law enforcement have
expressed
their as a compartmentalization of focus
and if something isn't within your
immediate purview very similar attitudes
have been seen I guess is the point so
that rings that Rings very very true
yeah I think that's it we have been
speaking with John kiriaku former CIA
counter-terrorism officer
um thank you so much for your time I
really appreciate it thank you this was
fun